[snorts]
>> War ravaging the East since 1937 and
Japan's [music] invasion of China
reached Europe on the 1st of September
1939 with Germany's invasion of Poland.
It became global on the 7th of December
1941 when Japanese aircraft attacked the
American naval base at Pearl Harbor.
It touched every continent
and lasted for 6 years.
It ended with a new weapon for a new
age.
This is the history [music] of the
greatest of all man-made events.
These men are part of that history.
They are eyewitnesses to the triumphs
and tragedies of the war wherever it was
fought.
Their testimony is part of the story of
how our world was made
by those who could pay
and those who could no longer meet
the price [music] of empire.
In the middle of 1942, the war in Europe
would reach its halfway point and its
turning point.
It had taken Hitler half a war to occupy
a tenth of the world's surface and
control [music] a population roughly
equivalent to that of the United States
of America. Half a war to gain an
empire.
It would take him half a war to lose
one.
Japan also [music] reached the halfway
point with a vast empire. It had
scorched across the Asia-Pacific region
until it occupied a sixth of the earth's
surface.
Then it too started to tumble towards
destruction.
"It is inconceivable," Winston Churchill
had declared in 1925,
"that in our lifetime and in that of our
children, Japan could pose a threat to
the security of the British Empire in
the East."
As late as 1939, he was being reassuring
about possible Japanese designs on
Singapore. "There will," he promised,
"be no attack in any period [music]
which our foresight can measure."
But there was.
The southern resources area was vital to
Japan. The price of silk, [music] still
Japan's principal export, had dropped by
50% since the Great Depression, and she
was resource poor.
Something had to be done.
By 1938, military spending absorbed 75%
of Japanese government [music]
expenditure.
She launched not one attack, but many.
The United States lost the use of all of
its Pacific battleships and large
numbers of cruisers and destroyers. The
British and Dutch Far Eastern fleets had
been eliminated, and the Royal
Australian Navy had been driven back to
port.
Japan had lost not a single battleship,
aircraft carrier, heavy or light
cruiser.
It had gained resources of great
importance, including 70% [music] of the
world's tin supply, most of its
production of natural rubber, and the
oil output of the Dutch East Indies,
which at the time exceeded that of Iran
and California [music] combined.
It had done this
>> [music]
>> in a single onslaught fought as two
campaigns
in Asia and in the Pacific.
We will look first at the Asian
offensive that conquered Hong Kong,
Malaya, Singapore, Burma, and the Dutch
East Indies.
The day after Pearl Harbor, Japanese
aircraft operating out of Vietnam bombed
Singapore and the Philippines was bombed
by planes flying out of Taiwan.
The new territories were invaded in the
first part of the capture of Hong Kong
and the two British capital ships in the
area, Prince of Wales and Repulse,
sailed from Singapore to contest
Japanese landings on the Malay
Peninsula. They had no air cover and on
the 10th of December, both were sent to
the bottom by waves of attacking
Japanese aircraft.
Thailand, then known as Siam, was
occupied on December the 9th [music] and
formally allied itself with Japan on the
14th.
>> Siam, another self-styled neutral who
frequently announced her intention of
defending herself against aggression,
she too has given way.
>> The Imperial Japanese Army could now
march through Thailand on route to
Burma, a journey that they would attempt
to hasten by construction of the
Burma-Thailand Railway, which was to
become so notorious.
On December the 15th, Japanese troops
entered Burma. The full-scale invasion
would be launched in January. On
December the 16th, they landed in
Borneo. On the 18th, they crossed onto
Hong Kong Island.
By the 7th of January, the Japanese had
Sarawak. They landed on the Celebes a
couple of days later, and British North
Borneo fell on the 19th.
>> This is a world war, and none can tell
how far it may spread. So, the Dutch
Empire in the Far East prepares.
>> The Dutch East Indies, which generated
1/7 of the Netherlands economy, was a
particularly crucial objective of the
Japanese campaign. Its annual production
of 65 million barrels of oil had the
potential to transform Japan's ability
to wage a protracted war.
But, the Dutch destroyed the wells.
On the Malay Peninsula, General Tomoyuki
Yamashita's 25th Imperial Japanese Army
was advancing.
Yamashita, whose exploits would earn him
the sobriquet Tiger of Malaya, had 150
tanks. They were not very good tanks,
which did not matter.
The British forces opposing him had no
tanks at all.
British defenses, weakened by supply of
resources to the war in Europe,
crumbled.
The Japanese advance through Malaya
followed two lines, across the Thai
border and down the west coast, and from
the landings [music] at Kota Bharu
following the east coast.
The British in Malaya formed defensive
lines, but failed to extend their
flanks.
They had not learned the lesson of the
German Blitzkrieg through the Ardennes,
and just as on the European battlefield,
their flanks were quickly turned by
enemy troops infiltrating through
supposedly impassable areas. In this
case, the jungle.
On December 31st, the last of the
British and Commonwealth forces crossed
the causeway,
evacuating Malaya and garrisoning the
island fortress of Singapore.
The greatest disaster in British
Imperial history was less than 2 months
away.
By mid-January, the commander-in-chief
of ABDACOM, the
American-British-Dutch-Australian
Command, General Wavell, who had been
kicked sideways from North Africa,
[music]
was ordering Arthur Percival, the
general officer commanding Malaya, to
prepare Singapore [music]
for a siege.
Before Singapore fell, Japanese [music]
forces working their way through the
Dutch East Indies, present-day
Indonesia, hopped from island to island
suppressing [music] what resistance they
found.
Small garrisons of Dutch and other
forces had been sent to defend some of
these islands, but their position was
hopeless, the planning rudimentary, and
their equipment inadequate. [music]
The fate of Gull Force, an Australian
formation sent to support Dutch troops
on the island of Ambon, was typical.
Gull Force reached Ambon on December
17th, just 2 weeks before the Japanese.
>> There were only about 1,100 of us, and
there would have been only about that
many Dutch
Dutch-led
Ambonese soldiers.
So, the action was very, very, brief,
and come end of January, early February,
the Dutch capitulated, and
cuz Australians had no option but to do
likewise. So, that's when I became a
prisoner of war.
>> The survivors were marching into 3 years
of harsh captivity.
The first Japanese landing on Singapore
on February the 8th occurred less than a
week after the fall of Ambon.
Four days later, a ship carrying
Australian nurses and wounded evacuated
from Singapore was bombed by Japanese
aircraft and sank.
Most of the survivors reached [music]
Bangka Island like Ambon in the Dutch
East Indies. An officer from their ship
surrendered to the Japanese who ordered
the 22 nurses and one civilian woman to
wade into the surf.
When they were waist deep, they were
machine gunned.
All but Sister Vivian Bullwinkel were
killed.
Sister Bullwinkel survived the war and
gave evidence before the war crimes
tribunal in Tokyo.
Of the massacre, she said,
"We just marched into the surf and they
fired at us.
There were no tears, for we knew it was
our [music] lot."
The day before the Bangka Island
massacre on the 15th of February,
General Percival had surrendered the
Singapore garrison of 130,000 troops to
an invading army half that size.
Facing a numerically superior enemy and
having taken about the same number of
casualties, 9,000, as the defenders,
Yamashita's call on the British to
surrender or face destruction [music]
was an enormous bluff.
But General Arthur Percival, baggy
shorts, scarecrow frame, and trim
mustache perfectly designed to be the
scapegoat for such a disaster, had
mainly raw troops without air cover with
which to meet battle-hardened Japanese.
His concern for the safety of
Singapore's 1 million civilians overrode
any other judgment, and he marched into
captivity at the head of his force, many
of whom would suffer dreadfully [music]
in the years ahead.
Yamashita could hardly believe his luck,
and said so.
As far as Japanese public opinion was
concerned, the improbable collapse of
the British Empire in the East meant
quite simply victory.
After the surrender of Singapore, the
headline of the Asahi Shimbun newspaper
trumpeted, "Situation of Pacific War
decided." And the jubilant Japanese
government distributed treats to all the
children.
With the fall of Singapore, 55,000
Indian soldiers of the King were taken
prisoner.
40,000 of them volunteered to fight in
the Indian National Army, a Japanese
creation under the respected leader
Subhas Chandra Bose, which purported to
be fighting the British for Indian
independence.
Later in 1942, [music]
Winston Churchill was to say in a speech
in London, "I have not become the King's
first minister in order to preside over
the liquidation of the British Empire."
But, of course, he had.
>> This war changed [music] everything.
End of the British Empire.
They won the war,
but they lost their empire.
>> The pomp and circumstance by which a
[music] few thousand held several
million in their sway had been exposed
for the frail bluff it was.
Singapore, fallen.
The empire was on the canvas, and though
it would rise again, it would be, as
they say, as a dead man walking.
The Japanese catchcry, "We are all
Asians." Their claim to be on a crusade
to evict the white man from Asia had
immediate resonance. But, like Hitler in
Europe, the Japanese knew how to
conquer, but not how to keep an empire.
Soon, they were hated and [music]
resented more violently than had been
the colonial masters.
Taking food from Chinese mouths, taking
[music] Korean women into sexual
slavery, using Filipinos for bayonet
practice was hardly the way.
But, those they conquered would not
return to the arms of their previous
masters. When the fighting ended, there
would be new paths to follow.
The Dutch colonial government relocated
to Australia at the beginning of March
as the tsunami of Japanese conquest
rolled through the East Indies,
effectively collapsing the Dutch Empire.
West from the Dutch Indies and from
Malaya, the battle was for Burma.
And that battle threatened to prize open
the door to India.
Japanese aircraft operating out of
Thailand had launched the first bombing
raid on the capital Rangoon on the 23rd
of December.
Japanese reinforcements arrived [music]
through January and began to press
towards the capital. Moulmein,
celebrated in the poetry of Rudyard
Kipling, fell at the end of the month.
>> We knew that we cannot sit on the
frontier all the time.
We have to go.
This little feeling of the
withdrawal from Burma
was taken as a personal
touching point that we after all fought.
But now nobody thinks we fought cuz we
came back.
And the feeling was that we must get a
chance
to
at least settle with the Japanese that
they are no no better than us.
>> The troops opposing the Japanese advance
were mainly Indian divisions which
combined with British units comprised
the Burma Army. In the north of the
country [music] were the Chinese fifth
and sixth armies commanded by the
American General Joe Stilwell, a
stringent character known as Vinegar
Joe.
The Japanese entered Rangoon on March
the 5th.
Two weeks later, a new general was put
in command of first Burma Corps.
His name was William Slim.
>> The Japanese is a tough enemy
and much must be done before he will
admit defeat.
>> By the end of April, the Japanese
[music] had cut the Burma Road.
General [music] Stilwell began his march
south to reunite with Allied forces on
May the 15th, he crossed into [music]
Assam in British India.
Five days later, after the longest
withdrawal in British military history,
1,000 [music] km, Bill Slim led Burma
Corps across the border into India. "The
men looked," Slim said, "like
scarecrows." But, he added, "They looked
like soldiers, [music] too."
>> We did not want the Japanese to come and
take over India.
Cuz there was a general feeling that the
Japanese will be much worse.
One person is evil,
but the other is even more evil.
>> It has been said that the winter saved
the Russians, and in Burma, the monsoon
saved the British. It would be 6 months
before the fight there was resumed.
>> I think I like to watch that.
>> The Japanese advance through the islands
of the Pacific had happened in the same
months as their onslaught [music] on
Asia and the East Indies and it had met
with a similarly great measure of
success.
Almost half of the Earth's water surface
is the Pacific Ocean. It covers an area
greater than all of the land masses
combined. Its scale dwarfs the scattered
parcels of dry land that rise above its
waves, but it was the existence of these
islands that made extending the
Co-Prosperity Sphere into the Pacific
feasible.
Because a ring [music] of fortified
islands made the Empire defensible.
And at Versailles, some of those islands
had been gifted to Japan. The Marshall,
Carolines and Marianas were former
German colonies. [music]
Two American outposts upset the
integrity of that defensive ring. They
were Wake and Guam.
Three days after Pearl Harbor, Japanese
forces landed on Guam which had
surrendered by 6:00 the same morning.
The first Japanese assault on Wake was
beaten off by a well-entrenched defense.
Stronger attempt on December the 23rd
succeeded and Wake surrendered that day.
The day before, December 22nd, the main
Japanese landings on Luzon signaled the
commencement of the battle for the
Philippines.
The American commander, General Douglas
MacArthur, had 130,000
men in uniform.
But 100,000 were Filipinos who [music]
had been trained in close order drill.
They could salute, but had never been in
a fight.
MacArthur began to withdraw his forces.
By the 5th of January, he had
successfully established one American
and seven Filipino divisions, 80,000
men, at Bataan, where they came under
sustained Japanese attack.
By the 22nd of January, MacArthur was
ordering the withdrawal of forces to his
final [music] defensive line,
an operation completed on the 26th.
On the 8th of February, Filipino
President Quezon proposed to President
Roosevelt that his country be granted
complete independence so that he could
proclaim Filipino neutrality, which he
hoped would oblige both American and
Japanese forces to leave.
President Roosevelt, advocate of
self-determination in the Atlantic
Charter, rejected Quezon's proposal, but
said that Filipino troops were free to
surrender if they wished.
He said that American forces would fight
to the end.
President Quezon left the Philippines on
February the 20th. General MacArthur
left on March the 11th. Both men went to
Australia. The Japanese continued to
reinforce their invasion, opening a
fierce [music] offensive against Bataan
on April the 3rd.
On the 9th of April, the Allied forces
on Bataan surrendered. 78,000 men were
marched into captivity.
This was [music] the Bataan Death March,
more than 100 km under the scorching sun
with hardly any food or water.
Amongst those who marched [music] into
captivity were 12,000 Americans, barely
a third of whom would survive Japanese
[music]
imprisonment.
Fighting elsewhere in the Philippines,
Mindanao, Luzon, Corregidor continued.
But by the 5th of May, General
Wainwright was obliged to surrender the
15,000 man garrison on [music]
Corregidor.
5 days later, on May the 10th, the last
Allied troops in the Philippines
surrendered.
Japanese troops had begun landing on New
Guinea on March the 8th.
Further landings followed and on March
the 22nd, Japanese planes bombed the
northern Australian port city of Darwin.
>> It was obvious that the Japanese were on
their way to invade us. And everything
was
haste.
And it was no trouble to get into the
army
as long as you could cough okay.
>> [laughter]
>> And that
you could say black or white,
you were in without any question.
And at the time I got in it was a week
before my 19th birthday.
>> By the time Douglas MacArthur had
established his command in Brisbane, the
situation he faced was almost entirely
black.
Virtually the whole of the Southwest
Pacific command area was now in Japanese
hands.
Germany first commitment that America
had made at the Washington conference
meant that he had limited strength on
which to rely.
But one national leader at least was
determined to face the Japanese
challenge as an overriding priority.
>> THE FULL CABINET TODAY
DIRECTED THE WAR CABINETS
to gazette the necessary REGULATIONS
FOR THE COMPLETE MOBILIZATION
OF ALL THE RESOURCES,
HUMAN AND MATERIAL,
IN THIS COMMONWEALTH FOR THE DEFENSE of
this Commonwealth. THAT MEANS THAT EVERY
HUMAN BEING IN THIS COUNTRY
is now, WHETHER HE OR SHE likes it, AT
THE SERVICE OF THE GOVERNMENT TO WORK IN
THE DEFENSE of Australia.
>> [applause]
>> John Curtin, the Australian Prime
Minister, exercised his right in a fiery
confrontation with Churchill to withdraw
Australian troops from the European war
to fight the enemy on his doorstep. By
March 1942, the majority of Australian
troops were back home, ready to fight in
the Pacific.
In determining which strategy Japan
should now follow, men in Tokyo had
disagreed.
Naval staff had pressed for occupation
of the southern part of New Guinea, from
where action could be launched against
New Caledonia, Fiji, and Samoa,
extending and strengthening the
defensive perimeter and isolating
Australia from United States support and
supply.
The Combined Fleet Staff, led by Admiral
Yamamoto, thought differently. It argued
for drawing the American Pacific Fleet
into a full-scale engagement and so it
believed to its destruction.
Fatally, but predictably, the result was
a face-saving compromise.
Both strategies would be adopted, which
meant that both would be weakened.
An invasion force to initiate the naval
staff strategy assembled at Rabaul.
On the 4th of May, the convoy sailed for
Port Moresby, the key to New Guinea.
Less than a week earlier, the American
carriers Hornet and Enterprise had left
Pearl Harbor with their battle groups
bound for the Coral Sea.
Two other carriers, Lexington and
Yorktown, had sailed 2 weeks previously.
On May the 4th, the Battle of the Coral
Sea was initiated when Yorktown launched
air strikes against the invasion fleet
from Rabaul.
The next day, the main Japanese strike
force built around the carriers Shokaku
and Zuikaku entered the Coral Sea.
The American and Japanese fleets engaged
without significant results on the 7th,
but around 0800 hours in the morning of
May the 8th, the carrier forces located
each other.
The first time those serving aboard
ships in a naval action never saw their
opponents.
The Lexington was hit and abandoned,
Shokaku disabled and forced to retire,
and Zuikaku, though undamaged, lost 40%
of her air group.
The consequences of all this were to be
enormous.
The fact that the Americans were obliged
to withdraw would allow the Japanese to
claim a victory, but it was a victory
that compelled Japan to abandon plans
for an invasion of New Guinea from the
sea.
Had they landed, they would have faced
Australian defenders who were present in
only brigade strength.
The Japanese, [music] as we We see,
decided instead to take Port Moresby by
an overland route.
Admiral Yamamoto's argument for an
alternative strategy had been
strengthened by an action on April the
18th that did little damage and took
only 50 lives.
On that day, 16 [music] specially
adapted B-25 bombers had taken off from
the carrier Hornet on a bombing raid
over Tokyo.
The raid is in the history books in the
name of its commander,
the Doolittle raid.
The aircraft did not have the range to
return to the carrier, so they flew on
to land in China, where [music] most
crashed.
Crews that crashed into Japanese [music]
hands became prisoners of war. Three
were shot by firing squad.
Crews that crashed in China survived.
But the real story was the impact on
Japan.
Bombs had fallen in Tokyo. Bombs had
fallen close to the Imperial Palace.
Bombs had threatened the life of the
emperor.
The shock and shame of this cried out
for a response from a military cast
whose first duty was to defend the
emperor.
Planning began for a counterblow which
would neutralize America's capacity to
launch raids on [music] the home
islands.
It was evident to Japanese planners that
flights from the nearby Chinese mainland
were a possibility, and so on April
21st, only a couple of days after the
Doolittle raid, Japan's Chinese
Expeditionary Army was ordered to knock
out airbases in Chekiang and Kiangsi.
By mid-May, the Chinese had been routed
east of Chekiang. A second Japanese army
advanced in late May and by early July
the expeditionary army had met all of
its objectives.
Before then, in May, Yamamoto's moment
had arrived. The action of the combined
fleet would finally neutralize American
naval strength in the Pacific and
importantly, deal with a small Hawaiian
outlier that had provided cover for
[music] the carriers from which the
Doolittle raiders flew. A place 3,100
km from [music] the nearest continent in
any direction.
Midway.
American code breakers led by Commander
Joseph [music] Rochefort knew that the
Imperial Japanese Navy was going to a
place designated AF, but they didn't
know where AF was.
A false message sent from American HQ to
the US fleet advised that Midway was
running short of fresh water. Snapping
at the [music] trap, the Japanese
relayed the message advising that AF was
short of water.
The US [music] fleet had the key to the
lock.
AF stood for Midway and the Imperial
Japanese Navy was going there.
Not much more than 60 ships were
involved in the battle.
Midway would not be decided [music] by
fleets of warships. It was the almost
500 aircraft that the opposing navies
would use like long-range cannon that
would settle the issue.
The Battle of the Coral Sea ruled the
carriers Shōkaku and Zuikaku out of the
attack on [music] Midway.
USS Yorktown, damaged in the same
battle, was estimated to require three
months for repair,
but 1,400
workmen completed the work in two days
and she took her place with the American
fleet. It takes many sorts [music] of
hero to win a war.
The Japanese sent a diversionary force
under Admiral Hosogaya north to the
Aleutians, but Admiral Chester W. Nimitz
commanding Pacific Ocean areas was not
distracted. He ordered his forces to
meet where he expected the main enemy
blow to fall at Midway.
Task Force 16, Admiral Raymond Spruance,
and Task Force 17, [music] Admiral Jack
Fletcher, sailed to their rendezvous
with each other, with the Japanese,
[music]
and with history.
And they sailed to meet an enemy that in
every measurable sense outgunned them.
The battle opened on June the 4th when
aircraft from Admiral Nagumo's first
striking force
attacked aircraft and installations
[music]
on Midway itself.
When the aircraft returned to the
carriers, the Admiral decided to
re-equip them with bombs rather than
torpedoes and launch a second attack on
the island.
His fleet was meanwhile [music]
repelling American aircraft attacks. The
Americans took significant losses with
no hits,
but not without effect.
The carrier forces were somewhat
dispersed, their fighter cover was
operating at low altitude, and flight
decks were crowded with rearming and
refueling aircraft.
10:20, Admiral Nagumo gave the order to
launch when ready. Within 5 minutes they
would launch and the Admiral would stand
on the brink of a great victory. They
were instead five minutes that
decisively changed the course of the
battle
and the war.
>> On that first day we had about 30 ships
of all types, battleships, cruisers,
destroyers, and fast transports.
Second day we had three carriers.
>> Any luck with them?
>> Oh, yes. Stuck right in there.
>> I'm a lucky man.
>> In those five minutes Commander Wade
McClusky of the USS Enterprise's bombing
six squadron led his 37 Dauntless dive
bombers in from 14,500
ft in a 70° dive at 280 knots.
The carrier Akagi was the [music] first
hit, then Kaga, last Soryu when
Yorktown's dive bombers joined the
assault.
Japan lost four carriers, more than
2,000 seamen, and 250 aircraft. This was
not, in terms of human life, a terrible
battle.
In terms of influence on history, it was
in the front rank.
Japanese losses equalized the strength
of the opposing fleets.
Between 1942 [music]
and 1944,
Japan would add six new fleet carriers.
The USA, 14.
In fact, through the war, for every
major naval vessel built in Japanese
shipyards, the Americans built 16.
The news of Midway [music] was passed to
Prime Minister Tojo in typically obtuse
language. The navy, he was told by
General Moritake Tanabe, has made a
great mistake.
Japan lost no territory as a result of
its mistake, but Midway's effects would
be felt when towards the end of 1943,
the Americans began to prize open the
defensive perimeter. Japan would have
inadequate ships and above all aircraft.
In 1942, [music]
Japan lost twice the number of aircraft
it produced.
As great naval forces clashed in the
war's first significant turning point at
Midway,
the war in Western Europe was being
confined almost entirely to the skies.
It was for a long time the only means
that Britain had of carrying the fight
to her enemy. 1/3 of Britain's national
output was devoted to the strategic air
offensive. When the war had started,
bombing was conducted according to
strict rules. In 1939,
the Chamberlain government had rejected
a suggestion that the Black Forest be
bombed on the grounds that much of it
was private property. But, to point out
the obvious, desperate times called for
desperate measures. Almost 150,000
Rolls-Royce Merlin engines were built.
The V12 power plant drove some of the
most famous planes [music] of the war,
Spitfire, Hurricane, Mosquito, Mustang,
and the four-engined Avro Lancaster.
The Lancaster was a true heavy bomber.
Its bomb load of 6.35 metric tons
overshadowed the B-17 Flying Fortress
and the German Heinkel 111 and Junkers
88, all of which carried between two and
three tons.
By general assent, the best night bomber
of the war, the Lancaster was not
without faults.
Because of poorly placed escape hatches,
the average survival rate for the
seven-man crew of a disabled Lancaster
was 1.3 [music]
persons. For the less glamorous Halifax,
it was 2.45.
>> The Avro Lancaster, most powerful and
efficient bomber in the world, and one
of the most important war-winning
weapons yet devised by the United
Nations.
>> The Lancaster [music] entered service
with Bomber Command of the Royal Air
Force at the same time as the G radio
navigation device came into use.
Such developments encouraged the RAF to
redefine its bombing strategy.
On February the 14th, [music] 1942, the
area bombing directive was issued.
It named the Ruhr, and specifically
Essen in the middle of that conurbation,
as primary targets with Duisburg,
Düsseldorf, and Cologne as other cities
[music] to be attacked.
>> The bomber offensive, undoubtedly, was a
major contribution to to to our winning
the war, no doubt about that. But, it
was a pretty ruthless business.
>> To drive home the strategy, a new head
of Bomber Command was appointed.
Arthur Harris, Bomber Harris, one of the
most controversial Allied commanders.
>> If you individually succeed,
you will have delivered the most
devastating blow against the very vitals
of the enemy.
Let him have it right on the chin.
Send that message to all groups and
stations.
>> That was how Air Marshal Harris,
Commander-in-Chief Bomber Command, gave
his instructions for the largest air
raid the world has ever known.
At aerodromes up and down the country,
well over a thousand British-built
bombers were being prepared for their
journey over the heart of Germany's
biggest
>> Harris was given a job. It was to
deliver on the objective of the area
bombing directive, and that document
explained that the purpose of dropping
bombs was
>> They don't know what they're dropping
when they drop them bombs. I don't care
what anybody says because I saw what it
was. They bombed everything.
Especially in Nuremberg. When I was
finally wound up in Nuremberg,
the lower Nuremberg was
level.
And the top of Nuremberg, that was
pretty well level, too.
It was pathetic to see all that. And
then you see the old people, the old
lady getting the bricks and knocking the
cement off. They were ready to rebuild.
They knew they lost the war, but they
weren't going to lose their lives, you
know?
>> Focus attacks on the morale of the enemy
civil population, and in particular,
industrial workers.
Area bombing remains perhaps the most
controversial of all of the military
strategies of the war.
Pre-war projections both [music]
stimulated expenditure on bombers and
advocacy of their use.
Official British planning was based on a
projected casualty rate of 50 casualties
per ton of bombs dropped. In the event,
the death toll for the London Blitz was
one per ton, and the overall death toll
in Germany was half that.
As early as 1941, even Winston Churchill
was beginning to doubt the prophecies
about the effectiveness of bombing.
>> [music]
>> "It is very disputable," he said,
"whether bombing by itself will be a
decisive factor in the present war."
Essen was first attacked on the night of
the 8th 9th of March, and then on March
the 28th 9th, the RAF attacked Lübeck.
aircraft attacked, 13 were lost. Lübeck
was virtually lost. Lübeck was a port
where engines [music] for U-boats were
manufactured. It was also an historical
medieval beautiful city, and it was laid
waste.
In retaliation, Hitler ordered attacks
on British cities that qualified as
targets because they were beautiful. All
they had in common was prominence in
tourist guides like the Baedeker, and
indeed the raids became known as the
Baedeker raids.
A raid on Augsburg with heavy losses
persuaded Harris to abandon daytime
bombing, and from late April Bomber
Command flew by night.
Rostock was attacked to great effect,
and at the end of May Cologne was hit in
the first 1,000 bomber raid. The
operational order was succinct. Object:
to destroy the city of Cologne.
Barely 2 days later, almost as great a
number hit Essen, and at the end of June
Bremen was the target.
Harris was until the very end of the war
unshakable in his belief that bombing
would bring Germany to her knees, but
the disruption to industry and the
effect on civilian morale, victims of
what was euphemistically called
dehousing, would hasten the end of the
war.
Area bombing had the advantage that it
did not depend on accurate or aiming,
which various reports had proved was
beyond the reach of current equipment.
The Butt report analyzing the
effectiveness of Bomber Command's
actions in the summer of 1941 had found
that only one in four bombers had
dropped their loads within 8 km [music]
of their targets. On nights when there
was no moon, it was only one in 20. In
fact, in 1941, Bomber Command had
suffered more casualties than it had
caused. Crews dying as the British
military historian Sir John Keegan put
it, largely to crater the German
countryside.
>> They'd had not arranged for
people who had done their 30 operations
to come back and say to us, "Listen
here, fellows, this is a sort of thing
that you've got to protect yourself
from, guys. When you're flying tight in
your flight at about so 7,000 ft or
10,000 ft, that'll be about the best
protection you can get." But they didn't
do that.
All we had was just raw recruits
doing bombing raids on Germany.
>> A mistake to suppose that the bombers
were attacking defenseless civilians.
The cities were well-defended. Indeed,
anti-aircraft [music]
defense tied up 1 million German service
personnel. And although it represented
only 7% of British military manpower,
[music]
Bomber Command took 24% of British
military deaths.
>> As we came out of the target area, I got
caught in his beam.
I thought of it a thousand times since
as to what
I did. Well, I was absolutely no doubt I
should have just remained at the same
height and flew and kept on changing
course.
But instead of that, I attempted to get
out of the beam by increasing my speed.
And I did that by diving.
Got free of the beam, but it wasn't very
long before the rear tail gunner was
reporting that we were being attacked.
A night fighter, again I had to take
whatever evasive action I thought was
appropriate.
Again, it was diving.
And as a result of this, of course, we
lost a lot of lost all my height.
I thought I was flying at somewhere
about
500 ft.
And as a result I hit a tree.
I
can remember the two of the crew coming
around and saying, "Come on, Carl,
you've got to get out of here."
And that's what I did.
The bomber aimer, who was in front of
me,
and the wireless operator,
they were killed in the crash.
And that left three of us.
>> The morality of area bombing continues
to be debated and its targeting of
civilian populations without regard to
age or gender has led to comparisons
with the criminal slaughter of the
Holocaust.
Course, bombing involved the risks of
war. It was not a cowardly assault on
defenseless civilians.
Tens of thousands of Allied airmen lost
their lives.
Surely the compelling distinction
dividing the death camps from the bomb
sites is that all sides used area
bombing because all sides believed that
it could and would be a war-winning
weapon.
No one outside the heart of Nazism has
ever pretended that killing Jews,
Romani, Slavs, and others was going to
affect the outcome of the war.